Preliminary Guide to the William Swinton Bennett Hopkins Papers, 1834-1946 (bulk 1852-1898)
William Swinton Bennett Hopkins papers 1834-1946, bulk 1852-1898
Hopkins, William Swinton Bennett
3.5 Linear Feet 1657 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Swinton Bennett Hopkins Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1983.
Biographical Note
Colonel in the 31st Massachusetts Volunteers during the Civil War and a prominent Mass. attorney and politician. His father was Erastus Hopkins, a noted Mass. clergyman.
Collection Overview
Collection consists largely of correspondence between family members, friends, and business associates spanning three generations, as well as some Civil War and early Reconstruction letters relating to Hopkins' activities in New Orleans. Correspondents include Hopkins' daughter, Elizabeth; her husband Alfred Lawrence Aiken, a prominent banker in Boston; the Gadsden family of Charleston, S.C.; and the Peck family, relatives of Hopkins' wife, Lizzie. An information folder chronologically lists a portion of the collection. Also included in this collection are a few legal papers, financial papers, addresses and writings, pictures, and a miscellaneous folder that includes some genealogy. Subjects mentioned in the letters include travel in the U.S. and Europe, marriage and family life, illness, Williams College, Yale College, politics, law,bloodletting with leeches, Civil War activities, and The Worcester Continentals.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Hopkins, William Swinton Bennett, b. 1836
Hopkins family
Gadson family
Peck family
Aiken, Alfred Lawrence
United States. Army -- Officers Correspondence
Reconstruction
Phlebotomy
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
United States -- Description and travel
Europe -- Description and travel
Legal documents
Genealogy
Contents of Collection
- Accession Sept. 2, 1983
  - Correspondence: 1834-1856 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: 1857-1862 March (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: 1862 April-1862 June (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: 1867 July-1871 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: 1872-1877 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: 1878-1880 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: 1881-1946, undated (Box 7)
  - Legal Papers: 1859, 1867, undated (Box 8)
  - Financial Papers: 1858-1880
  - Addresses and Writings: 1849-1882, undated
  - Miscellany: 1853-1880, undated
  - Pictures